<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties><title>Developer's Guide</title></properties>
<body>
<section>

    <h2>Developer's Guide</h2>
        <p>Here you find all information needed to contribute good code. These are
           naming conventions, heading comments, javadoc and unit tests.</p>

    <subsection name="Java file header">
        <p>For new class files this header is recommended.</p>
        <source><![CDATA[
/*
 *
 * The DbUnit Database Testing Framework
 * Copyright (C)2002-2008, DbUnit.org
 *
 * This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
 * modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
 * License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
 * version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
 *
 * This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
 * Lesser General Public License for more details.
 *
 * You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
 * License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
 * Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
 *
 */
        ]]></source>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Javadoc class header">
        <p>For java class definitions this header is recommended.</p>
        <source><![CDATA[
/**
 * @author <developer> (<sf-user-name> AT users.sourceforge.net)
 * @author Last changed by: $Author$
 * @version $Revision$ $Date$
 * @since <dbunit-version>
 */
        ]]></source>
        <p>Here an example:</p>
        <source><![CDATA[
/**
 * @author gommma (gommma AT users.sourceforge.net)
 * @author Last changed by: $Author$
 * @version $Revision$ $Date$
 * @since 2.4.0
 */
        ]]></source>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Javadoc for methods">
        <p>Besides the standard javadoc tags it is desired to also add the dbunit version
        in which the method was introduced. This lets users and developers keep track of
        the changes that are made to the old/existing API.</p>
        <source><![CDATA[
/**
 * @param myValue <some comment>
 * @since <dbunit-version>
 */
public void assertSomething(String myValue) {
...
        ]]></source>
    </subsection>


</section>
</body>
</document>