<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>About DbUnit</title>
    <author email="epugh@uopensourceconnections.com">Eric Pugh</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="About DbUnit">
    <p>
      DbUnit is a JUnit extension (also usable with Ant) targeted at database-driven projects that, 
      among other things, puts your database into a known state between test runs.  This is an excellent 
      way to avoid the myriad of problems that can occur when one test case corrupts the database and 
      causes subsequent tests to fail or exacerbate the damage.
    </p>
    <p>
      DbUnit has the ability to export and import your database data to and from XML datasets. 
      Since version 2.0, DbUnit can also work with very large datasets when used in streaming mode.
      DbUnit can also help you to verify that your database data match an expected set of values.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section name="News">
      <table border="1">
        <tr>
          <td>2010-08-31</td>
          <td>DbUnit project team is proud to deliver the new 2.4.8 release: please have a look at the <a href="changes-report.html#a2.4.8">changes</a> report for the release contents.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2009-11-09</td>
          <td>DbUnit project team is proud to deliver the new 2.4.7 release: please have a look at the <a href="changes-report.html#a2.4.7">changes</a> report for the release contents.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2009-10-09</td>
          <td>We wish to welcome Jeff Jensen as a DbUnit developer, the project team is growing!</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2009-09-24</td>
          <td>Another member joined the DbUnit project developers group: welcome John Hurst!</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2009-09-20</td>
          <td>Your contributions has led us to cut a new release: DbUnit 2.4.6 is out. Here a detailed <a href="changes-report.html#a2.4.6">changes</a> report.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2009-05-23</td>
          <td>Another bugfixing release has been cut: DbUnit 2.4.5 is out. Here a detailed <a href="changes-report.html#a2.4.5">changes</a> report.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2009-02-24</td>
          <td>We are proud to announce the 2.4.4 release has been cut. Here a detailed <a href="changes-report.html#a2.4.4">changes</a> report.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2009-01-20</td>
          <td>Development continues to go on, fixes and a additions have been contributed and a new 2.4.3 release has been cut. Here a detailed <a href="changes-report.html#a2.4.3">changes</a> report.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-12-17</td>
          <td>Some other fixes and a additions have been released in dbunit-2.4.2. Here a detailed <a href="changes-report.html#a2.4.2">changes</a> report.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-12-15</td>
          <td>Another Open Source project named <a href="http://jailer.sourceforge.net">Jailer</a> has added support for the DbUnit flat XML dataset file format. The integration provided by the Jailer project allows easy data sharing between the two projects. Well done Ralf!</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-12-03</td>
          <td>Previous version introduced a bug on Oracle-based tests, so we are proud to announce a quick new version (2.4.1) that fixes it. More information in the <a href="changes-report.html#a2.4.1">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-11-27</td>
          <td>DbUnit development is very active and is proud to announce the 2.4.0 release! Here are the <a href="changes-report.html#a2.4.0">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-09-11</td>
          <td>We all are so proud to announce the 2.3.0 release is finally out! Have a look at the <a href="changes-report.html#a2.3.0">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-06-08</td>
          <td>Matthias Gommeringer joined the project team. Welcome Matthias!</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-05-23</td>
          <td>Well another bug fixing release is out: 2.2.3 fixes some annoing bugs! Please see <a href="changes-report.html#a2.2.3">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-05-05</td>
          <td>Release 2.2.2 is out and fixes some annoing bugs! Please see <a href="changes-report.html#a2.2.2">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-03-19</td>
          <td><a href="http://dbunit.wikidot.com/">Wiki</a> is back.... again!</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-03-18</td>
          <td>Release 2.2.1 is finally out!!! See <a href="changes-report.html#a2.2.1">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-03-12</td>
          <td>S&#xe9;bastien Le Callonnec joined the project team.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2008-02-29</td>
          <td>Release 2.2.1 is on it's first steps. Snapshot release available on <a href="http://dbunit.sourceforge.net/repo/snapshots">DbUnit Snapshots Maven Repo</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2007-12-01</td>
          <td>Roberto Lo Giacco joined the project team.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2006-12-28</td>
          <td>Version 2.2 finally released!!!. See <a href="changes-report.html#a2.2">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>        
        <tr> 
          <td>2006-12-20</td>
          <td><a href="http://www.dbunit.org/cgi-bin/wiki.pl">Wiki</a> is back!. </td>
        </tr>        
        <tr> 
          <td>2006-05-28</td>
          <td>Build has been ported to <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven 2</a> and snapshots for the 2.2 release are available in the <a href="http://dbunit.sourceforge.net/repo/snapshots/">repository</a>. </td>
        </tr>        
        <tr> 
          <td>2006-02-04</td>
          <td>Felipe Leme joined the DbUnit developement team.</td>
        </tr>        
        <tr> 
          <td>2005-08-19</td>
          <td><b>Website Updated!</b> Link to wiki has been removed.  Many fixes in CVS for 2.2-dev, see <a href="changes-report.html#a2.2">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>      
        <tr> 
          <td>2004-05-31</td>
          <td>Version 2.1 released. Multiple bugfixes and enhancements. See <a href="changes-report.html#a2.1">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2004-04-28</td>
          <td>DeveloperWorks article: <a href="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/library/j-dbunit.html?ca=drs-j1604">Control your test-environement with DbUnit and Anthill</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2004-03-16</td>
          <td>The <a href="http://www.dbunit.org/wiki/">DbUnit Wiki</a> is now officially online. Please contribute to the <a href=" http://www.dbunit.org/cgi-bin/wiki.pl?SupportedRDBMS">SupportedRDBMS</a> page.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2004-01-26</td>
          <td>ONJava article: <a href="http://www.onjava.com/pub/a/onjava/2004/01/21/dbunit.html">Effective Unit Testing with DbUnit</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2004-01-22</td>
          <td>Version 2.0 released. See <a href="changes-report.html#a2.0">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2003-10-05</td>
          <td>Version 1.5.6 released. See <a href="changes-report.html#a1.5.6">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2003-07-16</td>
          <td>Federico Spinazzi joined the DbUnit developement team.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2003-07-16</td>
          <td>Version 1.5.5 released. See <a href="changes-report.html#a1.5.5">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2003-04-04</td>
          <td>Version 1.5.1 released. See <a href="changes-report.html#a1.5.1">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2003-03-01</td>
          <td>Version 1.5 released. See <a href="changes-report.html#a1.5">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2002-11-07</td>
          <td>Eric Pugh joined the DbUnit developement team.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2002-07-17</td>
          <td>The java API documentation is now available <a href="apidocs/index.html">online</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2002-07-17</td>
          <td>Version 1.4 released. See <a href="changes-report.html#a1.4">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2002-05-10</td>
          <td>Timothy Ruppert and Ben Cox joined the DbUnit developement 
         team.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2002-04-04</td>
          <td>Version 1.3 released. See <a href="changes-report.html#a1.3">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2002-04-04</td>
          <td>New website design and logo done by <a href="http://www.silphid.com/">Silphid 
         Creations</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2002-03-19</td>
          <td>Version 1.2.4 released. See <a href="changes-report.html#a1.2.4">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2002-03-15</td>
          <td>Version 1.2 released. See <a href="changes-report.html#a1.2">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2002-03-10</td>
          <td>Version 1.1 released. See <a href="changes-report.html#a1.1">changes</a>.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr> 
          <td>2002-02-27</td>
          <td>Version 1.0 released. This is the first public release.</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
  </section>

</body>
</document>
